Welcome to Bayeku,
اهلًا بكم في قرية بياكو
a riverine community in Ikorodu, Lagos --
مجتمع يُقيم على ضفة نهر في مدينة إكورودو في ولاية لاغوس
a vivid representation of several riverine communities across Nigeria,
نموذج حي لعدة مجتمعات تُقيم على ضفاف الأنهار على امتداد دولة نيجيريا
communities whose waterways have been infested
مجتمعات اجتاحت ممراتها المائية
by an invasive aquatic weed;
الأعشاب المائية الضارة المنتشرة بوفرة؛
communities where economic livelihoods have been hampered:
مجتمعات حيث سبل العيش فيها محاطة بعوائق اقتصادية
fishing, marine transportation
كصيد الأسماك والنقل البحري
and trading;
والتجارة؛
communities where fish yields have diminished;
مجتمعات حيث حصيلة صيد الأسماك في تناقص
communities where schoolchildren are unable to go to school
مجتمعات حيث لا يستطيع الطلبة الذهاب إلى المدارس
for days, sometimes weeks, on end.
لعدة أيام وأحياناً لأسابيع مستمرة.
Who would have thought that this plant
من كان يظن أن هذه النبتة
with round leaves, inflated stems, and showy, lavender flowers
ذات الأوراق المستديرة والسيقان السميكة والزهور الأرجوانية اللون
would cause such havoc in these communities.
قد تسبب دماراً لهذه المجتمعات.
The plant is known as water hyacinth
هذه النبتة تُعرف بورد النيل
and its botanical name, Eichhornia crassipes.
والاسم العلمي لها هو: Eichhornia crassipes.
Interestingly, in Nigeria, the plant is also known by other names,
من المثير في نيجيريا أن هذه النبتة تُعرف بعدة أسماء أخرى
names associated with historical events,
أسماء مرتبطة بأحداث تاريخية
as well as myths.
إضافة إلى الأساطير.
In some places, the plant is called Babangida.
تُسمى هذه النبتة في بعض الأماكن بابانجيدا (نسبة إلى الحاكم العسكري السابق)
When you hear Babangida, you remember the military and military coups.
عندما تسمع بابانجيدا، تتذكر الجيش والإنقلابات العسكرية.
And you think: fear, restraint.
وتفكر بالخوف والاضطهاد.
In parts of Nigeria in the Niger Delta, the plant is also known as Abiola.
في أنحاء أخرى من نيجيريا، تسمى هذه النبتة أبيولا في دلتا نيجيريا.
When you hear Abiola, you remember annulled elections
عندما تسمع أبيولا، تتذكر الانتخابات المُلغاة
and you think: dashed hopes.
وتفكر في الآمال التي تحطمت.
In the southwestern part of Nigeria,
في الجزء الجنوبي الغربي من نيجيريا،
the plant is known as Gbe'borun.
تُعرف هذه النبتة باسم "Gbe'borun"
Gbe'borun is a Yoruba phrase
"Gbe'borun" هي تعبير بلغة اليوروبا
which translates to "gossip," or "talebearer."
وتُترجم إلى "القيل والقال/النميمة"، أو ناشر الإشاعات
When you think of gossip, you think: rapid reproduction, destruction.
عندما تفكرُ بالقيل والقال، فإنك تفكرُ أيضاً بالتكاثر السريع والدمار،
And in the Igala-speaking part of Nigeria,
وفي الجزء الناطق بلغة Igala من نيجيريا،
the plant is known as A Kp'iye Kp'oma,
تُعرف هذه النبتة باسم A Kp'iye Kp'oma،
And when you hear that, you think of death.
وعندما تسمع هذا الاسم، فإنك تفكرُ بالموت.
It literally translates to "death to mother and child."
تترجم حرفياً إلى "الموت للأم والطفل".
I personally had my encounter with this plant in the year 2009.
صادفتُ شخصياً هذه النبتة في عام 2009.
It was shortly after I had relocated from the US to Nigeria.
بعد فترة وجيزة من انتقالي من أمريكا إلى نيجيريا
I'd quit my job in corporate America
بعد أن استقلت من عملي في الشركات الأمريكية
and decided to take this big leap of faith,
وقررت أن أغتنم فرصة ثقتي بهذا الانتقال المفاجىء الكبير
a leap of faith that came out of a deep sense of conviction
جاءت هذه الثقة السريعة من إحساس عميق بالإيمان والإقتناع الراسخ
that there was a lot of work to do in Nigeria
بأن هناك الكثير من المشاريع في نيجيريا
in the area of sustainable development.
في مجال التنمية المستدامة.
And so here I was in the year 2009,
ولذلك كنت هنا في 2009،
actually, at the end of 2009,
في الحقيقة كنتُ هنا في نهاية 2009،
in Lagos on the Third Mainland Bridge.
في جزيرة لاغوس على جسر البر الرئيسي الثالث.
And I looked to my left and saw this very arresting image.
نظرتُ إلى يساري فشاهدت هذه الصورة اللافتة للنظر.
It was an image of fishing boats
كانت صورة لقوارب صيد الأسماك
that had been hemmed in by dense mats of water hyacinth.
المُحاطة بهذا البساط الكثيف من ورد النيل سميك الساق.
And I was really pained by what I saw
وتألمتُ حقاً بما رأيته
because I thought to myself,
وقلت لنفسي،
"These poor fisherfolk,
"هؤلاء الصيادين الفقراء
how are they going to go about their daily activities
كيف لهم القيام بأنشطتهم اليومية
with these restrictions."
مع هذه العراقيل."
And then I thought, "There's got to be a better way."
ثم فكرت، لا بدّ وأن هناك طريقة أفضل
A win-win solution whereby the environment is taken care of
حلً مربح ونتائجه مفيدة للطرفين بواسطته يتم الاعتناء بالبيئة
by the weeds being cleared out of the way
بإزالة الأعشاب عن الممرات المائية
and then this being turned into an economic benefit
ومن ثم يتم تحويلها إلى منفعة إقتصادية
for the communities whose lives are impacted the most
للمجتمعات الأكثر تأثراً
by the infestation of the weed.
بسبب اجتياح هذه الأعشاب الضارة.
That, I would say, was my spark moment.
أود القول أن هذه كانت لحظة إنطلاقي.
And so I did further research to find out more
لذا قمت بعمل أبحاث إضافية لمعرفة المزيد
about the beneficial uses of this weed.
عن الاستخدامات المفيدة لهذه الأعشاب الضارة.
Out of the several, one struck me the most.
واحدٌ من بين عدة أشياء استوقفتني وأدهشتني للغاية.
It was the use of the plant for handicrafts.
كان استخدام هذه النبتة في الحرف اليدوية
And I thought, "What a great idea."
وفكرتُ: "يا لها من فكرة عظيمة."
Personally, I love handicrafts,
أنا شخصياً أحب الأعمال اليدوية،
especially handicrafts that are woven around a story.
لا سيّما تلك الأعمال اليدوية التي تُنسج حولها قصة.
And so I thought, "This could be easily deployed within the communities
حتى أنني فكرتُ: "هذا يمكن أن ينتقل ويتم تداولة بسرعة داخل المجتمعات
without the requirement of technical skills."
دون الحاجة إلى المهارات التقنية الفنية."
And I thought to myself, "Three simple steps to a mega solution."
و قلتُ لنفسي، " ثلاثُ خطوات بسيطة لحل رائع وجدير بالملاحظة."
First step: Get out into the waterways and harvest the water hyacinth.
الخطوة الأولى: الخروج إلى الممرات المائية وحصاد ورد النيل سميك الساق.
That way, you create access.
بهذا تنطلق العملية
Secondly, you dry the water hyacinth stems.
الخطوة الثانية: تجفيف جذوع ورد النيل.
And thirdly, you weave the water hyacinth into products.
والخطوة الثالثة: نسج ورد النيل وتحويله إلى منتوجات.
The third step was a challenge.
كانت الخطوة الثالثة تحدياً
See, I'm a computer scientist by background
أنا عالمة حاسوب ولدي خلفية بهذا العلم
and not someone in the creative arts.
لكن لا أملك أي معرفة بالفنون الإبداعية
And so I began my quest
لهذا بدأت بحثي
to find out how I can learn how to weave.
لمعرفة كيف يمكنني أن أتعلم كيفية النسج
And this quest took me to a community in Ibadan, where I lived,
وقادني هذا البحث إلى مجتمع في إيبادان، حيث كنت أعيش،
called Sabo.
يُدعى سابو.
Sabo translates to "strangers' quarters."
تُترجم سابو إلى "أبناء المستوطنات الغرباء".
And the community is predominantly made up of people
يتكون المجتمع في أغلبيته من أشخاص
from the northern part of the country.
من الجزء الشمالي من البلاد.
So I literally took my dried weeds in hand,
وحملتُ فعلاً في يدي الأعشاب الضارة المجففة
there were several more of them,
كان هناك الكثير منها
and went knocking from door to door to find out who could teach me
وطفتُ أطرقُ باباً وراء باب أبحث عن من يستطيع تعليمي
how to weave these water hyacinth stems into ropes.
كيف أنسج من جذوع ورد النيل حبالاً
And I was directed to the shed of Malam Yahaya.
فتم إرشادي بالذهاب إلى كوخ ملام يحيى
The problem, though, is that Malam Yahaya doesn't speak English
وعلى الرغم من أن ملام يحيى لا يتحدث الإنجليزية
and neither did I speak Hausa.
ولا اللغة الهوسية التي أتحدث بها.
But some little kids came to the rescue
لكن جاء بعض الصبية الصغار لإنقاذ الموقف
and helped translate.
وساعدوا في الترجمة.
And that began my journey of learning how to weave
كانت هذه بداية رحلتي في تعلم كيفية النسج
and transform these dried water hyacinth stems
وتحويل جذوع ورد النيل المجففة
into long ropes.
إلى حبال طويلة
With my long ropes in hand,
وعندما كانت الحبال الطويلة التي نسجتها في يدي
I was now equipped to make products.
أصبحت حينها جاهزة لعمل منتجات
And that was the beginning of partnerships.
من هنا بدأت شراكات العمل
Working with rattan basket makers to come up with products.
مع صناع السلال المصنوعة من النخيل القصبي لتحويلها إلى منتجات
So with this in hand, I felt confident
وأنا أحمل هذا في يدي، شعرتُ بالثقة
that I would be able to take this knowledge
أنه بإمكاني نقل هذه المعرفة
back into the riverine communities
مرةً أخرى إلى المجتمعات النهرية
and help them to transform their adversity into prosperity.
ومساعدتهم على تحويل محنتهم إلى ازدهار.
So taking these weeds and actually weaving them
وهكذا أخذنا هذه الأعشاب الضارة ونسجناها فعلاً
into products that can be sold.
وحولناها إلى مصنوعات يمكن بيعها.
So we have pens, we have tableware,
لدينا أقلام وأدوات لطاولة المائدة
we have purses, we have tissue boxes.
لدينا محافظ نقود وشنط يد وعلب مناديل.
Thereby, helping the communities
وبالتالي ساعدنا المجتمعات
to see water hyacinth in a different light.
لرؤية ورد النيل في أشكال مختلفة ومبهجة.
Seeing water hyacinth as being valuable,
رؤية ورد النيل كشيء ذو قيمة
being aesthetic, being durable, tough, resilient.
كرمز جمالي دائم وقوي ومرن.
Changing names, changing livelihoods.
وغيرنا المُسميات وسبل العيش أيضاً.
From Gbe'borun, gossip,
فمن مسمى Gbe'borun "النمّام"،
to Olusotan, storyteller.
إلى Olusotan "الحكواتي".
And from A Kp'iye Kp'oma, which is "killer of mother and child,"
ومن A Kp'iye Kp'oma، "قاتل الأم والطفل"،
to Ya du j'ewn w'Iye kp'Oma,
إلى Ya du j'ewn w'Iye kp'Oma
"provider of food for mother and child."
"معيل الأم والطفل."
And I'd like to end with a quote by Michael Margolis.
أود أن أنهي باقتباس لمايكل مارغوليس.
He said, "If you want to learn about a culture, listen to the stories.
قال: "إذا أردت معرفة ثقافة ما، فاستمع إلى القصص.
And if you want to change a culture, change the stories."
وإذا أردت تغيير ثقافة ما، فغيّر القصص."
And so, from Makoko community, to Abobiri, to Ewoi,
وهكذا، من مجتمع Makoko إلى Abobiri إلى Ewoi،
to Kolo, to Owahwa, Esaba,
إلى Kolo، إلى Owahwa و Esaba،
we have changed the story.
قُمنا بتغيير القصة.
Thank you for listening.
شكراً لكم على استماعكم
(Applause)
(تصفيق)